[Music]
here we tackle back propagation the core
algorithm behind how nural networks
learn after a quick recap for where we
are the first thing I'll do is an
intuitive walkthrough for what the
algorithm is actually doing without any
reference to the formulas then for those
of you who do want to dive into the math
the next video goes into the calculus
underlying all this if you watch the
last two videos or if you're just
jumping in with the appropriate
background you know what a neural
network is and how it feeds forward
information here we're doing the classic
example of recognizing handwritten
digits whose pixel values get fed into
the first layer of the network with 784
neurons and I've been showing a network
with two hidden layers having just 16
neurons each and an output layer of 10
neurons indicating which digit the
network is choosing as its answer I'm
also expecting you to understand
gradient descent as described in the
last video and how what we mean by
learning is that we want to find which
weights and biases minimize a certain
cost function as a quick reminder for
the cost of a single training example
what you do is take the output that the
network gives along with the output that
you wanted it to give and you just add
up the squares of the differences
between each component doing this for
all of your tens of thousands of
training examples and averaging the
results this gives you the total cost of
the network and as if that's not enough
to think about as described in the last
video the thing that we're looking for
is the negative gradient of this cost
function which tells you how you need to
change all of the weights and biases all
of these connections so as to most
efficiently decrease the
cost back propagation the topic of this
video is an algorithm for computing that
crazy complicated gradient and the one
idea from the last video that I really
want you to hold firmly in your mind
right now is that because thinking of
the gradient Vector as a direction in
13,000 Dimensions is to put it lightly
beyond the scope of our imaginations
there's another way you can think about
it the magnitude of each component here
is telling you how sensitive the cost
function is to each weight and bias for
example let's say you go through the
process I'm about to describe and you
compute the negative gradient and the
component associated with the weight on
this edge here comes out to be 3.2 while
the component associated with this edge
here comes out as
0.1 the way you would interpret that is
that the cost of the function is 32
times more sensitive to changes in that
first weight so if you were to wiggle
that value just a little bit it's going
to cause some change to the cost and
that change is 32 times greater than
what the same wiggle to that second
weight would
give personally when I was first
learning about back propagation I think
the most confusing aspect was just the
notation and the index chasing of it all
but once you unwrap what each part of
this algorithm is really doing each
individual effect that it's having is
actually pretty intuitive it's just that
there's a lot of little adjustments
getting layered on top of each other so
I'm going to start things off here with
a complete disregard for the notation
and just step through those effects that
each training example is having on the
weights and
biases because the cost function
involves averaging a certain cost per
example over all the tens of thousands
of training examples the way that we
adjust the weights and biases for a
single gradient descent step also
depends on every single example or
rather in principle it should but for
computational efficiency we're going to
do a little trick later to keep you from
needing to hit every single example for
every single step in either case right
now all we're going to do is focus our
attention on one single example this
image of a two what effect should this
one training example have on how the
weights and biases get
adjusted let's say we're at a point
where the network is not well trained
yet so the activations in the output are
going to look pretty random maybe
something like 0.5 0 .8 0.2 on and on
now we can't directly change those
activations we only have influence on
the weights and biases but it is helpful
to keep track of which adjustments we
wish should take place to that output
layer and since we want it to classify
the image as a two we want that third
value to get nudged up while all of the
others get nudged down moreover the
sizes of these nudges should be
proportional to how far away each
current value is from its Target value
for example the increase to that number
two neuron's activation is in a sense
more important than the decrease to the
number eight neuron which is already
pretty close to where it should
be so zooming in further let's focus
just on this one neuron the one whose
activation we wish to increase remember
that activation is defined as a certain
weighted sum of all of the activations
in the previous layer plus a bias which
is all then plugged into something like
the sigmoid squish function or a railu
so there are three different avenues
that can team up together to help
increase that activation you can
increase the bias you can increase the
weights and you can change the
activations from the previous layer
focusing just on how the weights should
be adjusted notice how the weights
actually have differing levels of
influence the connections with the
brightest neurons from the preceding
layer have the biggest effect since
those weights are multiplied by larger
activation values
so if you were to increase one of those
weights it actually has a stronger
influence on the ultimate cost function
than increasing the weights of
connections with dimmer neurons at least
as far as this one training example is
concerned remember when we talk about
gradient descent we don't just care
about whether each component should get
nudged up or down we care about which
ones give you the most bang for your
butt this by the way is at least
somewhat reminiscent of a theory in
Neuroscience for how biological networks
of neurons learn heian theory often
summed up in the phrase neurons that
fire together wire together here the
biggest increases to weights the biggest
strengthening of connections happens
between neurons which are the most
active and the ones which we wish to
become more active in a sense the
neurons that are firing while seeing a
two get more strongly linked to those
firing when thinking about a to to be
clear I really am not in a position to
make statements one way or another about
whether artif IAL networks of neurons
behave anything like biological brains
and this fires together wire together
idea comes with a couple meaningful
asterisks but taken as a very loose
analogy I do find it interesting to note
anyway the third way that we can help
increase this neuron's activation is by
changing all the activations in the
previous layer namely if everything
connected to that digit 2 neuron with a
positive weight got brighter and if
everything connected with a negative
weight got dimmer then that digit 2
neuron would become more
active and similar to the weight changes
you're going to get the most bang for
your buck by seeking changes that are
proportional to the size of the
corresponding
weights now of course we cannot directly
influence those activations we only have
control over the weights and biases but
just as with the last layer it's helpful
to just keep a note of what those desire
changes are but keep in mind zooming out
one step here this is only what that
digit 2 output neuron wants remember we
also want all of the other neurons in
the last layer to become less active and
each of those other output neurons has
its own thoughts about what should
happen to that second to last
layer so the desire of this digit 2
neuron is added together with the
desires of all the other output neurons
for what should happen to this second to
last layer again in proportion to the
corresponding weights and in proportion
to how much each of those neur needs to
change this right here is where the idea
of propagating backwards comes in by
adding together all these desired
effects you basically get a list of
nudges that you want to happen to the
second to last layer and once you have
those you can recursively apply the same
process to the relevant weights and
biases that determine those values
repeating the same process I just walked
through and moving backwards through the
network and zooming out a bit further
remember that this is all just how a
single training example wishes to nudge
each one of those weights and biases if
we only listen to what that two wanted
the network would ultimately be
incentivized just to classify all images
as a two so what you do is you go
through this same back propop routine
for every other training example
recording how each of them would like to
change the weights and the biases and
you average together those desired
changes
[Music]
this collection here of the averaged
nudges to each weight and bias is
Loosely speaking the negative gradient
of the cost function referenced in the
last video or at least something
proportional to it I say Loosely
speaking only because I have yet to get
quantitatively precise about those
nudges but if you understood every
change that I just referenced why some
are proportionally bigger than others
and how they all need to be added
together you understand the Mechanics
for what back propagation is actually
doing by the way in practice it takes
computers an extremely long time to add
up the influence of every single
training example every single gradient
descent step so here's what's commonly
done instead you randomly shuffle your
training data and then divide it into a
whole bunch of mini batches let's say
each one having 100 training examples
then you compute a step according to the
mini batch it's not going to be the
actual gradient of the cost function
which depends on all of the training
data not this tiny subset so it's not
the most efficient step downhill but
each mini batch does give you a pretty
good approximation and more importantly
it gives you a significant computational
speed up if you were to plot the
trajectory of your network under the
relevant cost surface it would be a
little more like a drunk man stumbling
aimlessly down a hill but taking quick
steps rather than a carefully
calculating man determining the exact
downhill direction of each step before
taking a very slow and careful step in
that
direction this technique is referred to
as stochastic gradient
descent there's kind of a lot going on
here so let's just sum it up for
ourselves shall we back propagation is
the algorithm for determining how a
single training example would like to
nudge the weights and biases not just in
terms of whether they should go up or
down but in terms of what relative
proportions to those changes caus the
most rapid decrease to the cost a true
gradient descent step would involve
doing this for all your tens and
thousands of training examples and
averaging the desired changes that you
get but that's computationally slow so
instead you randomly subdivide the data
into these mini batches and compute each
step with respect to a mini batch
repeatedly going through all of the mini
batches and making these adjustments you
will converge towards a local minimum of
the cost function which is to say your
network is going to end up doing a
really good job on the training
examples so with all of that said every
line of code that would go into
implementing backprop actually
corresponds with something that you have
now seen at least in informal terms but
sometimes knowing what the math does is
only half the battle and just
representing the damn thing is where it
gets all muddled and confusing so for
those of you who do want to go deeper
the next video goes through the same
ideas that were just presented here but
in terms of the underlying calculus
which should hopefully make it a little
more familiar as you see the topic in
other resources before that one thing
worth emphasizing is is that for this
algorithm to work and this goes for all
sorts of machine learning Beyond just
neural networks you need a lot of
training data in our case one thing that
makes handwritten digits such a nice
example is that there exists the mnist
database with so many examples that have
been labeled by humans so a common
challenge that those of you working in
machine learning will be familiar with
is just getting the labeled training
data that you actually need whether
that's having people label tens of
thousands of images or whatever other
data type you might be dealing with
[Music]